Ever since I was a little girl
منذ ان كنت فتاة صغيرة
seeing "Star Wars" for the first time,
مشاهدة (حرب النجوم) لاول مرة
I've been fascinated by this idea
كنت مسحورة بهذه الفكرة
of personal robots.
فكرة الروبوتات الشخصية
And as a little girl,
و كفتاة صغيرة
I loved the idea of a robot that interacted with us
احببت فكرة ان الروبوت يتفاعل معنا
much more like a helpful, trusted sidekick --
كثيرا مثل صديق مساعد موثوق
something that would delight us, enrich our lives
شيئ يبهجنا ,و يثري حياتنا
and help us save a galaxy or two.
و يساعدنا في انقاذ مجرة او اثنتين
I knew robots like that didn't really exist,
هكذا عرفت ان الروبوتات مثل هذه غير موجودة فعلا
but I knew I wanted to build them.
لكني عرفت اني اريد بنائها
So 20 years pass --
و هكذا مرت 20 عاما
I am now a graduate student at MIT
الان انا طالبة دراسات عليا في معهد ماساشوستس للتقنية
studying artificial intelligence,
ادرس الذكاء الاصطناعي
the year is 1997,
العام 1997
and NASA has just landed the first robot on Mars.
انزلت وكالة ناسا اول روبوت على سطح المريخ
But robots are still not in our home, ironically.
و من السخرية لا تزال الروبوتات ليست في منازلنا
And I remember thinking about
و اتذكر هذا جعلني افكر
all the reasons why that was the case.
بكل الاسباب لماذا كانت تلك هي الحالة
But one really struck me.
لكن ما صدمني فعلا
Robotics had really been about interacting with things,
هو ان الروبوتات كانت فعلا للتعامل مع الاشياء
not with people --
ليس الاشخاص
certainly not in a social way that would be natural for us
بالتأكيد ليس بطريقة تكون طبيعية لنا
and would really help people accept robots
و تساعد الناس كثيرا في قبول الروبوتات
into our daily lives.
في حياتنا اليومية
For me, that was the white space; that's what robots could not do yet.
بالنسبة لي كانت تلك المساحة الخالية ذلك ما كانت الروبوتات لا تستطيع فعلة بعد
And so that year, I started to build this robot, Kismet,
و في تلك السنة بدأت بناء هذا الروبوت , كيسميت
the world's first social robot.
اول روبوت اجتماعي في العالم
Three years later --
و هكذا بعد ثلاثة سنوات
a lot of programming,
الكثير من البرمجة
working with other graduate students in the lab --
العمل مع طلاب اخرين في المختبر
Kismet was ready to start interacting with people.
كيسميت كان مستعدا للتفاعل مع الناس
(Video) Scientist: I want to show you something.
العالم : اريد ان اريك شيئا
Kismet: (Nonsense)
-----------
Scientist: This is a watch that my girlfriend gave me.
العالم : هذه ساعة اهدتني اياها صديقتي
Scientist: Yeah, look, it's got a little blue light in it too.
العالم: نعم, انظر ولديها ضوء ازرق صغير ايضا
I almost lost it this week.
كدت ان افقدها هذا الاسبوع
Cynthia Breazeal: So Kismet interacted with people
و هكذا كيسميت تفاعل مع الناس
like kind of a non-verbal child or pre-verbal child,
مثل طفل لا يستطيع الكلام بعد
which I assume was fitting because it was really the first of its kind.
و افترض ان ذلك كان مناسبا لانه كان فعلا الاول من نوعه
It didn't speak language, but it didn't matter.
لم يتحدث لغة لكن ذلك كان غير مهم
This little robot was somehow able
هذا الروبوت استطاع بطريقة ما
to tap into something deeply social within us --
ان يصل الي شيء ما اجتماعي عميقا داخلنا
and with that, the promise of an entirely new way
و مع ذلك الوعد بطريقة جديدة كليا
we could interact with robots.
بامكاننا ان نتفاعل مع الروبوتات
So over the past several years
و هكذا خلال العدة سنوات الماضية
I've been continuing to explore this interpersonal dimension of robots,
كنت اواصل استكشاف هذا البعد الشخصي للروبوتات
now at the media lab
الان في مختبر الوسائط
with my own team of incredibly talented students.
مع فريقي من الطلاب الموهوبين بشكل لا يصدق
And one of my favorite robots is Leonardo.
و واحد من روبوتاتي المفضلة هو ليوناردو
We developed Leonardo in collaboration with Stan Winston Studio.
طورنا ليوناردو مع استديو ستان ونستون
And so I want to show you a special moment for me of Leo.
و اريد ان اريكم لحظة خاصة لـ ليو بالنسبة لي
This is Matt Berlin interacting with Leo,
هذا هو مات بيرلين يتفاعل مع ليو
introducing Leo to a new object.
يقدم الى ليو شيء جديد
And because it's new, Leo doesn't really know what to make of it.
و لانه جديد ليو لا يعرف ماذا يفعل به
But sort of like us, he can actually learn about it
و نوعا ما مثلنا يستطيع نوعا ما ان يتعلم عنه
from watching Matt's reaction.
من مشاهدة رد فعل مات
(Video) Matt Berlin: Hello, Leo.
مات: مرحبا ليو
Leo, this is Cookie Monster.
ليو هذا وحش الكعك
Can you find Cookie Monster?
هل تستطيع ايجاد وحش الكعك؟
Leo, Cookie Monster is very bad.
ليو , وحش الكعك سيء جدا
He's very bad, Leo.
انه سيء جدا ليو
Cookie Monster is very, very bad.
وحش الكعك سيء جدا جدا
He's a scary monster.
انه وحش مخيف
He wants to get your cookies.
انه يريد اخذ كعكك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
CB: All right, so Leo and Cookie
حسنا , اذن ليو و كوكي
might have gotten off to a little bit of a rough start,
ربما بدءا بداية صعبة بعض الشيء
but they get along great now.
لكنهما يتفقان جيدا الان
So what I've learned
اذن ما تعلمته
through building these systems
من بناء هذه الانظمة
is that robots are actually
ان الروبوتات هي في الحقيقة
a really intriguing social technology,
تقنية اجتماعية مثيرة للاهتمام
where it's actually their ability
حيث ان قدرتها الفعلية
to push our social buttons
لضغط على ازرارنا الاجتماعية
and to interact with us like a partner
و تتفاعل معنا مثل شريك
that is a core part of their functionality.
وهذا جزء اساسي من وظيفتها
And with that shift in thinking, we can now start to imagine
و بهذا التغير في التفكير بدأنا في تخيل
new questions, new possibilities for robots
اسئلة جديدة , امكانيات جديدة للروبوتات
that we might not have thought about otherwise.
اننا قد لا نكون فكرنا فيها خلاف ذلك
But what do I mean when I say "push our social buttons?"
لكن ماذا اعني عندما اقول تضغط على ازرارنا الاجتماعية ؟
Well, one of the things that we've learned
حسنا , احد الاشياء التي تعلمناها
is that, if we design these robots to communicate with us
ان لو نحن صممنا هذه الروبوتات لتتواصل معنا
using the same body language,
بأستعمال نفس لغة الجسد
the same sort of non-verbal cues that people use --
نفس النوع من الاشارات غير اللفظية التي يستخدمها االبشر
like Nexi, our humanoid robot, is doing here --
مثل نكسي روبوتنا الشبيه بالانسان
what we find is that people respond to robots
ما نجده هو أن الناس تستجيب للروبوتات
a lot like they respond to people.
كثيرا مثلما يستجيبون للبشر
People use these cues to determine things like how persuasive someone is,
الناس تستخدم هذه الاشارات لتحديد أشياء مثل كيفية اقناع شخص ما
how likable, how engaging,
مقدار تحببه , مقدار اشتراكه
how trustworthy.
مقدار جدارته بالثقة
It turns out it's the same for robots.
لقد اتضح انه نفس الشيء عن الروبوتات
It's turning out now
لقد اتضح الان
that robots are actually becoming a really interesting new scientific tool
ان الروبوتات أصبحت في الواقع أداة علمية جديدة مثيرة للاهتمام حقا
to understand human behavior.
لفهم السلوك البشري
To answer questions like, how is it that, from a brief encounter,
لاجابة سؤال مثل كيف ذلك , من لقاء موجز
we're able to make an estimate of how trustworthy another person is?
نحن قادرون على تقدير جدارة شخص آخر بالثقة
Mimicry's believed to play a role, but how?
يعتقد ان التقليد يلعب دور, لكن كيف ؟
Is it the mimicking of particular gestures that matters?
هل هو تقليد حركات معينة هو المهم
It turns out it's really hard
لقد اتضح انه صعب حقا
to learn this or understand this from watching people
لتعلم هذا او فهم هذا من مشاهدة الناس
because when we interact we do all of these cues automatically.
لاننا عندما نتفاعل نفعل كل هذه الاشارات تلقائيا
We can't carefully control them because they're subconscious for us.
نحن لا نستطيع السيطرة عليها بعناية لانها لاوعي بالنسبة لنا
But with the robot, you can.
لكن مع الروبوتات تستطيع
And so in this video here --
و هكذا في الفيديو هنا
this is a video taken from David DeSteno's lab at Northeastern University.
هذا هو شريط فيديو مأخوذ من مختبر ديفيد ديستينو في جامعة نورث إيسترن
He's a psychologist we've been collaborating with.
انه طبيب نفسي كنا نتعامل معه
There's actually a scientist carefully controlling Nexi's cues
هنالك في الحقيقة عالم يتحكم في اشارات نكسي بعناية
to be able to study this question.
لنكون قادرين على دراسة هذه المسألة
And the bottom line is -- the reason why this works is
وخلاصة القول السبب في ان هذا يعمل
because it turns out people just behave like people
لأنه تبين الناس تتصرف تماما مثل الناس
even when interacting with a robot.
حتى عند التفاعل مع روبوت
So given that key insight,
اذن باعطاء هذه الفكرة المفتاحية
we can now start to imagine
بامكاننا ان نبدأ في تخيل
new kinds of applications for robots.
انواع جديدة من التطبيقات للروبوتات
For instance, if robots do respond to our non-verbal cues,
على سبيل المثال، إذا استجابت الروبوتات لاشاراتنا غير اللفظية
maybe they would be a cool, new communication technology.
ربما يكونو رائعين , وسيلة اتصال جديدة
So imagine this:
اذن تخيلو هذا
What about a robot accessory for your cellphone?
ماذا عن روبوت ملحق بهاتفك الجوال ؟
You call your friend, she puts her handset in a robot,
تتصل بصديقتك هي تضع هاتفها في روبوت
and, bam! You're a MeBot --
و بام! انت (ميبوت)
you can make eye contact, you can talk with your friends,
يمكنك عمل اتصال بالعين, تستطيع التحدث مع اصدقائك
you can move around, you can gesture --
تستطيع الحركة , تستطيع الاشارة
maybe the next best thing to really being there, or is it?
ربما يكون ثاني افضل شيء لكونك هناك حقا, او هو كذلك؟
To explore this question,
لاستكشاف هذا السؤال
my student, Siggy Adalgeirsson, did a study
طالبي سيجي ادالجيرسون قام بدراسة
where we brought human participants, people, into our lab
حيث احضرنا اناس مشاركين الى مختبرنا
to do a collaborative task
للقيام بمهمة تعاونية
with a remote collaborator.
مع متعاون من بعيد
The task involved things
المهمة تضمنت اشياء
like looking at a set of objects on the table,
مثل النظر الى مجموعة من الاشياء على الطاولة
discussing them in terms of their importance and relevance to performing a certain task --
مناقشتها من حيث اهميتها و ملائمتها لاداء مهمة معينة
this ended up being a survival task --
هذا انتهى الى كونها مهمة للبقاء على قيد الحياة
and then rating them in terms
وبعد ذلك تقييمها من حيث
of how valuable and important they thought they were.
قيمتها و اهميتها على حسب اعتقادهم
The remote collaborator was an experimenter from our group
المتعاون من بعيد كان مختبر من مجموعتنا
who used one of three different technologies
حيث استخدمو واحد من ثلاثة تكنولوجيات مختلفة
to interact with the participants.
للتفاعل مع المشاركين
The first was just the screen.
اذن الاول كان عبارة عن الشاشة
This is just like video conferencing today.
فقط مثل مؤتمرات الفيديو اليوم
The next was to add mobility -- so, have the screen on a mobile base.
الثاني كان باضافة حركة اذن كانت الشاشة على جهاز محمول
This is like, if you're familiar with any of the telepresence robots today --
هذا مثلما اذا كنت علي دراية باي من روبوتات الوجود عن بعد اليوم
this is mirroring that situation.
هذا يعكس تلك الحالة
And then the fully expressive MeBot.
ثم الـ (ميبوت) المعبر الكامل
So after the interaction,
اذن بعد التفاعل
we asked people to rate their quality of interaction
سألنا الناس لتقييم جودة تفاعلهم
with the technology, with a remote collaborator
مع التكنولوجيا , مع المتعاون من بعد
through this technology, in a number of different ways.
من خلال هذه التقنية في عدد من الطرق المختلفة
We looked at psychological involvement --
نظرنا الي المشاركة النفسية
how much empathy did you feel for the other person?
ما مقدار التعاطف التي تشعر به ناحية الشخص الاخر
We looked at overall engagement.
نظرنا الى الارتباط العام
We looked at their desire to cooperate.
نظرنا الى رغبتهم في المشاركة
And this is what we see when they use just the screen.
وهذا ما نراه عند استعمال الشاشة فقط
It turns out, when you add mobility -- the ability to roll around the table --
اتضح انه عند اضافة الحركة -القدرة على التحرك حول الطاولة -
you get a little more of a boost.
تحصل على دفعة اكثر بقليل
And you get even more of a boost when you add the full expression.
و تحصل على دفعة اكثر عند اضافة التعبير الكامل
So it seems like this physical, social embodiment
اذن يبدو مثل تجسيد مادي للاجتماعية
actually really makes a difference.
في الواقع يصنع فرقا بحق
Now let's try to put this into a little bit of context.
الان دعونا نحاول وضع هذا في القليل من السياق
Today we know that families are living further and further apart,
اليوم نحن نعلم ان العائلات تعيش ابعد و ابعد عن بعضها
and that definitely takes a toll on family relationships
و هذا طبعا يأخذ تأثيره على علاقات العائلة
and family bonds over distance.
و الروابط العائلية على بعد
For me, I have three young boys,
بالنسبة لي لدي ثلاثة اولاد صغار
and I want them to have a really good relationship
و اريدهم ان يكون لديهم علاقة جيدة فعلا
with their grandparents.
مع اجدادهم
But my parents live thousands of miles away,
لكن والدي يعيشان على بعد آلاف الاميال
so they just don't get to see each other that often.
لهذا لا يرون بعضهم كثيرا
We try Skype, we try phone calls,
جربنا (سكايب) جربنا الاتصالات الهاتفية
but my boys are little -- they don't really want to talk;
لكن اولادي صغار لايريدون الكلام فعلا
they want to play.
يريدون ان يلعبوا
So I love the idea of thinking about robots
انهم يحبون فكرة التفكير في الروبوتات
as a new kind of distance-play technology.
كنوع جديد من تكنولوجيا اللعب عن بعد
I imagine a time not too far from now --
هكذا انا اتخيل في زمن ليس بعيد جدا من الان
my mom can go to her computer,
تستطيع امي الذهاب الى حاسوبها
open up a browser and jack into a little robot.
تفتح متصفح وتدخل الى روبوت صغير
And as grandma-bot,
و كروبوت الجدة
she can now play, really play,
تستطيع الان ان تلعب, تلعب فعلا
with my sons, with her grandsons,
مع ابنائي , مع احفادها
in the real world with his real toys.
في العالم الحقيقي بالعابه الحقيقية
I could imagine grandmothers being able to do social-plays
بامكاني تخيل الجدات ان يكن قادرات على القيام بأدوار اجتماعية
with their granddaughters, with their friends,
مع حفيداتهن مع اصدقائهن
and to be able to share all kinds of other activities around the house,
و امكانية المشاركة في كل انواع النشاطات حول المنزل
like sharing a bedtime story.
مثل المشاركة في قصة قبل النوم
And through this technology,
و عن طريق هذه التقنية
being able to be an active participant
امكانية ان تكون مشارك فعال
in their grandchildren's lives
في حياة احفادك
in a way that's not possible today.
بطريقة غير ممكنة اليوم
Let's think about some other domains,
دعونا نفكر في بعض المجالات الاخرى
like maybe health.
مثل ربما الصحة
So in the United States today,
اذن في الولايات المتحدة اليوم
over 65 percent of people are either overweight or obese,
اكثر من 65% من الناس اما يعانون ن زيادة الوزن او السمنة
and now it's a big problem with our children as well.
الان هي مشكلة كبيرة مع اطفالنا ايضا
And we know that as you get older in life,
و نحن نعلم انه مع زيادتك في العمر
if you're obese when you're younger, that can lead to chronic diseases
إذا كنت بدينا عندما كنت أصغر سنا ، هذا يمكن أن يؤدي إلى أمراض مزمنة
that not only reduce your quality of life,
هذا لا يقلل فقط من نوعية حياتنا
but are a tremendous economic burden on our health care system.
ولكن يشكل عبئا اقتصاديا كبيرا على نظامنا للرعاية الصحية
But if robots can be engaging,
لكن اذا كان بامكان الروبوتات ان تكون مشاركة
if we like to cooperate with robots,
اذا اردنا ان نتعاون مع الروبوتات
if robots are persuasive,
اذا كانت الروبوتات مقنعة
maybe a robot can help you
ربما يستطيع روبوت مساعدتك
maintain a diet and exercise program,
في الحفاظ على نظام غذائي و برنامج تمارين
maybe they can help you manage your weight.
ربما يمكن أن تساعدك على إدارة وزنك
Sort of like a digital Jiminy --
نوع مثل صالة تمارين رقمية
as in the well-known fairy tale --
كالقصة الخيالية المعروفة جيدا
a kind of friendly, supportive presence that's always there
نوع من الصداقة الداعمة الموجودة هناك دائما
to be able to help you make the right decision
لتكون قادرة على مساعدتك على اتخاذ القرار الصحيح
in the right way at the right time
بالطريقة الصحيحة في الوقت الصحيح
to help you form healthy habits.
لمساعدتك في تكوين عادات صحية
So we actually explored this idea in our lab.
لذلك نحن في الواقع استكشفنا هذه الفكرة في مختبرنا
This is a robot, Autom.
هذا الروبوت أوتوم
Cory Kidd developed this robot for his doctoral work.
كوري كيد طور هذا الروبوت لعمله في الدكتوراه
And it was designed to be a robot diet-and-exercise coach.
و تم تصميمه ليكون روبوت حمية و مدرب تمارين
It had a couple of simple non-verbal skills it could do.
و كان لديه زوج من المهارات البسيطة الغير لفظية باستطاعته ان يفعلها
It could make eye contact with you.
يمكنه ان يتواصل معك بصريا
It could share information looking down at a screen.
بأمكانه ان يشارك معلومات بالنظر الى شاشة
You'd use a screen interface to enter information,
انت تستخدم واجهة الشاشة لادخال معلومات
like how many calories you ate that day,
كعدد السعرات الحرارية التي اكلتها ذلك اليوم
how much exercise you got.
كم من التمارين قمت بها
And then it could help track that for you.
و بعد ذلك يمكنه متابعة ذلك لك
And the robot spoke with a synthetic voice
و تكلم الروبوت بصوت صناعي
to engage you in a coaching dialogue
لتضمينك في حوار التدريب
modeled after trainers
على غرار المدربين
and patients and so forth.
و المرضى و هكذا
And it would build a working alliance with you
و سيكون بناء تحالف عمل معكم
through that dialogue.
عن طريق ذلك الحوار
It could help you set goals and track your progress,
ويمكن أن تساعدك على تحديد الأهداف ورصد التقدم الذي احرزته
and it would help motivate you.
ويمكن ان تساعد على تشجيعك
So an interesting question is,
ذلك سؤال مثير للاهتمام انه
does the social embodiment really matter? Does it matter that it's a robot?
هل يهم حقا تجسيد الاجتماعية؟ هل يهم انه روبوت؟
Is it really just the quality of advice and information that matters?
هل ما يهم حقا هو فقط نوعية النصيحة و المعلومات؟
To explore that question,
اذن لحل هذا السؤال
we did a study in the Boston area
قمنا بعمل دراسة في منطقة بوسطون
where we put one of three interventions in people's homes
حيث وضعنا واحدة من ثلاثة تدخلات في بيوت الناس
for a period of several weeks.
لمدة عدة اسابيع
One case was the robot you saw there, Autom.
احدها كان الروبوت الذي رأيتموه هناك أوتوم
Another was a computer that ran the same touch-screen interface,
آخر كان حاسب لديه نفس واجهة الشاشة اللمسية
ran exactly the same dialogues.
لديه نفس الحوارات
The quality of advice was identical.
نوعية النصيحة كانت متطابقة
And the third was just a pen and paper log,
بينما الثالث كان عبارة عن سجل ورقة و قلم
because that's the standard intervention you typically get
لان هذا هو التدخل الذي تحصل عليه عادة
when you start a diet-and-exercise program.
عندما تبدأ برنامج حمية وتمارين
So one of the things we really wanted to look at
اذن احد الاشياء التي اردنا النظر اليها فعلا
was not how much weight people lost,
ليس كم من الوزن خسر الناس
but really how long they interacted with the robot.
لكن لكم من الزمن تفاعلوا مع الروبوت
Because the challenge is not losing weight, it's actually keeping it off.
لان التحدي لم يكن خسارة الوزن لكن ابقاءه كذلك
And the longer you could interact with one of these interventions,
و كلما طالت مدة تفاعلك مع احد هذه التدخلات
well that's indicative, potentially, of longer-term success.
حسنا هذا يدل، ربما، الى النجاح على المدى الطويل
So the first thing I want to look at is how long,
اذن اول شيء اريد ان انظر الى كم من الزمن
how long did people interact with these systems.
كم من الزمن تفاعل الناس مع هذه الانظمة
It turns out that people interacted with the robot
لقد اتضح ان الناس تفاعلت مع الروبوت
significantly more,
اكثر بشكل ملحوظ
even though the quality of the advice was identical to the computer.
حتى ولو كانت نوعية النصيحة متطابقة مع الحاسب
When it asked people to rate it on terms of the quality of the working alliance,
عندما طلبت من الناس التقييم على حسب تحالف العمل
people rated the robot higher
قيم الناس الروبوت اعلى
and they trusted the robot more.
و وثقوا بالروبوت اكثر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And when you look at emotional engagement,
و عندما ننظر الى الارتباط العاطفي
it was completely different.
كان مختلف تماما
People would name the robots.
الناس سمت الروبوتات
They would dress the robots.
البستهم ملابس
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And even when we would come up to pick up the robots at the end of the study,
حتى عندما اتينا لاخذ الروبوتات عند نهاية الدراسة
they would come out to the car and say good-bye to the robots.
كانو يأتون للسيارة ويودعون الروبوتات
They didn't do this with a computer.
لم يفعلوا ذلك مع حاسوب
The last thing I want to talk about today
اخر شيء اريد التحدث عنه اليوم
is the future of children's media.
هو مستقبل اعلام الاطفال
We know that kids spend a lot of time behind screens today,
نحن نعلم ان الاطفال يقضون كثير من الوقت خلف الشاشات اليوم
whether it's television or computer games or whatnot.
سواء كان التلفاز او العاب الحاسوب او ما الى ذلك
My sons, they love the screen. They love the screen.
اولادي يحبون الشاشة . انهم يحبون الشاشة
But I want them to play; as a mom, I want them to play,
لكني اريدهم ان يلعبوا ; كأم اريدهم ان يلعبوا
like, real-world play.
مثل اللعب في العالم الحقيقي
And so I have a new project in my group I wanted to present to you today
و هكذا لدي مشروع جديد في مجموعتي اردت ان اقدمه لكم اليوم
called Playtime Computing
يدعى حوسبة وقت اللعب
that's really trying to think about how we can take
هذا هو في الحقيقة محاولة للتفكير
what's so engaging about digital media
في ماهو الجذاب حول وسائل الاعلام الرقمية
and literally bring it off the screen
وجلبه حرفيا خارج الشاشة
into the real world of the child,
الى عالم الطفل الحقيقي
where it can take on many of the properties of real-world play.
حيث يمكن ان يأخذ الكثير من خصائص اللعب في العالم الحقيقي
So here's the first exploration of this idea,
اذن هذا هو اول استكشاف لهذه الفكرة
where characters can be physical or virtual,
حيث يمكن للشخصيات ان تكون فعلية او افتراضية
and where the digital content
و حيث المحتوى الرقمي
can literally come off the screen
يستطيع حرفيا الخروج من الشاشة
into the world and back.
الى العالم والرجوع مرة اخرى
I like to think of this
انا احب ان افكر في هذا
as the Atari Pong
كلعبة بونغ من اتاري
of this blended-reality play.
من لعب هذا الواقع المخلوط
But we can push this idea further.
لكن يمكننا دفع هذه الفكرة ابعد
What if --
ماذا لو
(Game) Nathan: Here it comes. Yay!
(اللعبة)ناثان: هاهي تأتي , ياي!
CB: -- the character itself could come into your world?
سينثيا: الشخصية نفسها تستطيع الخروج الى عالمك؟
It turns out that kids love it
لقد اتضح ان الاطفال يحبونها
when the character becomes real and enters into their world.
عندما تصبح الشخصية حقيقية و تخرج الى عالمهم
And when it's in their world,
و عندما تكون في عالمهم
they can relate to it and play with it in a way
يمكن ان يتصلوا بها و يلعبوا معها بطريقة
that's fundamentally different from how they play with it on the screen.
تختلف كليا عن الطريقة التي لعبوا بها على الشاشة
Another important idea is this notion
فكرة مهمة اخرى هي هذا المفهوم
of persistence of character across realities.
وجود الشخصية عبر الواقع
So changes that children make in the real world
اذن التغيرات التي يفعلها الاطفال في العالم الحقيقي
need to translate to the virtual world.
تحتاج ان تترجم الى العالم الافتتراضي
So here, Nathan has changed the letter A to the number 2.
اذن هنا ناثان غير الحرف A الى الرقم 2
You can imagine maybe these symbols
تستطيع التخيل ربما هذه الرموز
give the characters special powers when it goes into the virtual world.
تعطي الشخصية قدرات خاصة عندما ترجع الى العالم الافتراضي
So they are now sending the character back into that world.
اذن الان هم يرسلون الشخصية الى ذلك العالم
And now it's got number power.
و الان لديها قوة الرقم
And then finally, what I've been trying to do here
و اخيرا ما كنت احاول عمله هنا
is create a really immersive experience for kids,
هو خلق تجربة غامرة حقا للأطفال،
where they really feel like they are part of that story,
حيث يشعرون حقا انهم جزء من تلك القصة
a part of that experience.
جزء من تلك التجربة
And I really want to spark their imaginations
و اردت حقا اشعال مخيلاتهم
the way mine was sparked as a little girl watching "Star Wars."
كما اشتعلت مخيلتي كفتاة صغيرة اشاهد (حرب النجوم)
But I want to do more than that.
لكن اريد ان افعل اكثر من ذلك
I actually want them to create those experiences.
انا اريدهم فعلا ان يخلقوا تلك التجارب
I want them to be able to literally build their imagination
اريدهم ان يكونوا قادرين على بناء مخيلاتهم حرفيا
into these experiences and make them their own.
في هذه التجارب و جعلها خاصة بهم
So we've been exploring a lot of ideas
هكذا كنا نستكشف الكثير من الافكار
in telepresence and mixed reality
في الوجود عن بعد و الواقع المخلوط
to literally allow kids to project their ideas into this space
للسماح للاطفال بعرض افكارهم حرفيا في هذا الفضاء
where other kids can interact with them
حيث يمكن لاطفال اخرين التفاعل معهم
and build upon them.
و البناء عليه
I really want to come up with new ways of children's media
انا اردت فعلا ايجاد طرق جديدة لاعلام الاطفال
that foster creativity and learning and innovation.
تتبنى الابداع والتعلم و الابتكار
I think that's very, very important.
انا اعتقد ان ذلك مهم جدا جدا
So this is a new project.
اذن هذا هو المشروع الجديد
We've invited a lot of kids into this space,
لقد دعونا الكثير من الاطفال الى هذا الفضاء
and they think it's pretty cool.
و هم يعتقدون انه رائع جدا
But I can tell you, the thing that they love the most
لكني استطيع ان اخبركم ان اكثر شيء يحبوه
is the robot.
هو الروبوت
What they care about is the robot.
ما يهمهم هو الروبوت
Robots touch something deeply human within us.
الروبوتات تلمس شيء انساني عميقا داخلنا
And so whether they're helping us
و سواء اذا كانوا يساعدونا
to become creative and innovative,
لنصبح خلاقين و مبدعين
or whether they're helping us
او كانوا يساعدوننا
to feel more deeply connected despite distance,
على الشعور العميق بالاتصال رغم بعد المسافة
or whether they are our trusted sidekick
او ما اذا كانوا مساعدينا الموثوقين
who's helping us attain our personal goals
الذين يساعدونا للوصول الى اهدافنا الشخصية
in becoming our highest and best selves,
في أن نصبح أنفسنا أعلى وأفضل،
for me, robots are all about people.
بالنسبة لي الروبوتات هي كل شيء عن الناس
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)